Okay, now in this lecture we're going to look at the second retrieval optimization method
which is through metadata filtering.
So what is metadata filtering?
Metadata filtering allows you to filter query results based on specific attributes attached
to your vectors.
So what it means is that metadata filtering allows you to reduce the number of vector embeddings
that you search based on certain specific attributes.
Now let's go and try and understand this to an example.
Now let's say you built an HR chatbot and your employees are both based out of India
and US.
Let's say you have the first document which has HR policies related to employees in India
and let's say mainly they are in a finance department and then you have the second HR policy
document which is focused on employees in US and let's say their department is mainly
manufactured.
Now let's say we have this end user who is based out of India and works in the finance
department.
So maybe he asks a question how many leaves can I take?
Now once this user query has been converted into vector embeddings there is going to be similarity
search so it's going to search for similar vectors in both these documents.
Now with metadata filtering what you do is you add certain tags to each document.
So let's say once I upload this document and our data source let's assume S3.
So once I upload this document I will also add this metadata.json tag and it's a very
simple file something like this which says okay employee India department finance.
So when you upload the document related to the US employees.
So here you will say employee USA department manufacturing and this is a JSON file that
you are going to upload with each of these documents.
So now what the metadata filtering does is once this user poses the same question based
on this metadata.json file so it's going to look for a vector embeddings only related
to this file and not this one.
So use metadata filters with query operations to find the vectors that match both similarity
criteria and specific metadata conditions.
And as I explained it's not going to look at vector embeddings and do a similarity search
for both documents only for this document one because it meets the specific metadata conditions
that we have defined in this.json file.
So what are the benefits benefits of metadata filtering?
It reduces the number of chunks that are being searched because we are not searching for
all the documents only the ones which meet the specific criteria.
Then in the cost of querying the vector store and then finally it also helps in improvement
in accuracy.
So benefits related to accuracy and cost.
Okay so that's pretty much it from this lecture as in the next lecture.